<NGSEP version="3.3.1" date="08-03-2019">
<title>Next Generation Sequencing Experience Platform</title>

<command id="FastqErrorsCorrection" class="ngsep.sequences.FastqFileErrorCorrector" printHelp="false">
<intro>
Corrects errors in fastq files based on k-mer abundance
</intro>
<title>Fixing sequencing errors</title>
<description>
Builds a k-mer abundance profile and use this profile to identify and correct sequencing errors
</description>
<argument>FASTQ_FILE</argument>
<argument>OUTPUT_FILE</argument>
<option id="m" type="INT" default="5" attribute="minCount">
Minimum k-mer abundance to consider a k-mer real
</option>
</command>

<command id="ReadsAligner" class="ngsep.alignments.ReadsAligner" printHelp="false">
<intro>
Aligns sequencing reads to a reference genome
</intro>
<title>Aligning reads to reference genomes</title>
<description>
Calculates a list of genomic regions for sites where the reads can be find in the reference genome
</description>
<argument>FMINDEX_FILE</argument>
<argument>READS_FILE</argument>
<argument>ALIGNMENTS_FILE</argument>
<option id="p" type="DOUBLE" default="0.7" attribute="minProportionKmers">
Minimum proportion of k-mers to select alignments
</option>
</command>

<command id="GenomeIndexer" class="ngsep.genome.GenomeIndexer" printHelp="false">
<intro>
Creates a FMINDEX for Indexing the genome
</intro>
<title>Indexing genome reference files</title>
<description>
Create a binary file containing a FMINDEX from genome
</description>
<argument>GENOME_FILE</argument>
<argument>OUTPUT_FILE</argument>
<option id="t" type="INT" default="100" attribute="tallyDistance">
Distance between tally indexes
</option>
</command>

<command id="MultisampleVariantsDetector" class="ngsep.discovery.MultisampleVariantsDetector">
<intro>Module for direct calculation of variants from multiple samples.</intro>
<title>Calling variants over multiple samples</title>
<description>
This modules allows to call variants over a group of samples separated by files or read group tags.
This is now the recommended method to perform variants detection on genotype-by-sequencing (GBS), RAD sequencing,
whole exome sequencing (WES), RNA-seq and low coverage (less than 10x) whole genome sequencing (WGS) data.
Although it can also be used on high coverage WGS data, the classic sample-by-sample analysis
(commands FindVariants, MergeVariants and MergeVCF) is still recommended to identify structural variants.
Requires one or more read alignment files in SAM or BAM format and the reference genome that was used to produce the alignments.
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>BAM_FILE*</argument>
<option id="r" type="GENOME" attribute="genome">
Fasta file with the reference genome.
</option>
<option id="o" type="FILE" defaultConstant="DEF_OUTPUT_FILE" attribute="outFilename">
Output file.
</option>
<option id="h" type="DOUBLE" defaultConstant="DEF_MIN_HETEROZYGOSITY_RATE_DIPLOID" attribute="heterozygosityRate">
Heterozygosity rate.
</option>
<option id="querySeq" type="STRING" attribute="querySeq">
Call variants just for this sequence.
</option>
<option id="first" type="INT" attribute="queryFirst">
Call variants just from this position in the given query sequence.
</option>
<option id="last" type="INT"  attribute="queryLast">
Call variants just until this position in the given query sequence.
</option>
<option id="ignoreLowerCaseRef" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="ignoreLowerCaseRef">
Ignore sites where the reference allele is lower case.
</option>
<option id="maxAlnsPerStartPos" type="INT" defaultConstant="DEF_MAX_ALNS_PER_START_POS" attribute="maxAlnsPerStartPos">
Maximum number of alignments allowed to start at the same reference site.
This parameter helps to control false positives produced by PCR amplification artifacts.
In this command, this filter is executed independently for each read group.
For GBS or RAD sequencing data use a large value such as 100.
</option>
<option id="p" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="processNonUniquePrimaryAlignments">
Process non unique primary alignments in the pileup process.
The default behavior is to process alignments that are unique (see option -minMQ).
</option> 
<option id="s" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="processSecondaryAlignments">
Consider secondary alignments in the pileup process. Non-unique primary alignments will also be considered in this mode.
</option>
<option id="minQuality" type="INT" defaultConstant="DEF_MIN_QUALITY" attribute="minQuality">
Minimum variant quality. In this command, this filter applies to the QUAL column of the VCF, which is
calculated for each variant as the maximum of the genotype qualities of samples with non-homozygous reference genotype calls.
See the command FilterVCF to apply filters of quality and read depth on individual genotype calls.
</option>
<option id="maxBaseQS" type="INT" defaultConstant="DEF_MAX_BASE_QS" attribute="maxBaseQS">
Maximum value allowed for a base quality score. Larger values will be equalized to this value.
</option>
<option id="ignore5" type="INT" default="0" attribute="basesToIgnore5P">
Ignore this many base pairs from the 5' end of the reads.
</option>
<option id="ignore3" type="INT" default="0" attribute="basesToIgnore3P">
Ignore this many base pairs from the 3' end of the reads.
</option>
<option id="knownSTRs" type="FILE" attribute="knownSTRsFile">
File with known short tandem repeats (STRs). This is a text file with at least three
columns: chromosome, first position and last position. Positions should be 1-based and
inclusive.
</option>
<option id="knownVariants" type="FILE" attribute="knownVariantsFile">
VCF file with variants to be genotyped. Only these variants will appear in the output VCF.
</option>
<option id="embeddedSNVs" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="callEmbeddedSNVs">
Flag to call SNVs within STRs. By default, STRs are treated as a single locus and hence no SNV will be called within an STR.
</option>
<option id="minMQ" type="INT" defaultConstant="DEF_MIN_MQ" attribute="minMQ">
Minimum mapping quality to call an alignment unique
</option>
<option id="ploidy" type="INT" defaultConstant="DEF_PLOIDY" attribute="normalPloidy">
Default ploidy of the samples.
</option>
<option id="psp" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="printSamplePloidy">
Print id and ploidy of the sample in the VCF header.
The header generated with this option is not a standard VCF header. However, it helps NGSEP to keep track of the ploidy of the samples through downstream analyses
</option>
</command>

<command id="FindVariants" class="ngsep.discovery.VariantsDetector">
<intro>The classic module of NGSEP for variants detection in individual samples.</intro>
<title>Calling variants on individual samples with the variants detector</title>
<description>
This is the classic module of NGSEP to call SNVs, small indels and structural
variants from sequencing data of single individuals. Basic usage requires an
alignments file in BAM format, the reference genome that was used to
produce the alignments, and a prefix for the output files.
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>REFERENCE</argument>
<argument>INPUT_FILE</argument>
<argument>OUTPUT_PREFIX</argument>
<option id="h" type="FLOAT" default="0.001">
Heterozygosity rate
</option>
<option id="querySeq" type="STRING">
Call variants just for this sequence.
</option>
<option id="first" type="INT">
Call variants just from this position in the given query sequence.
</option>
<option id="last" type="INT">
Call variants just until this position in the given query sequence.
</option>
<option id="ignoreLowerCaseRef">
Ignore sites where the reference allele is lower case.
</option>
<option id="maxAlnsPerStartPos" type="INT" default="5">
Maximum number of alignments allowed to start at the same reference site.
This parameter helps to control false positives produced by PCR amplification artifacts.
For GBS or RAD sequencing data use a large value such as 100.
</option>
<option id="p">
Process non unique primary alignments in the pileup process. 
The default behavior is to process alignments that are unique (see option -minMQ) 
</option> 
<option id="s">
Consider secondary alignments in the pileup process. Non-unique primary alignments will also be considered in this mode.
</option>
<option id="csb">
Calculate a exact fisher test p-value for strand bias between the reference and the alternative allele
</option>
<option id="minQuality" type="INT" default="0">
Minimum genotype quality to accept a SNV call.
</option>
<option id="maxBaseQS" type="INT" default="0 (No limit)">
Maximum value allowed for a base quality score. Larger values will be equalized to this value.
</option>
<option id="ignore5" type="INT" default="0">
Ignore this many base pairs from the 5' end of the reads.
</option>
<option id="ignore3" type="INT" default="0">
Ignore this many base pairs from the 3' end of the reads.
</option>
<option id="knownSTRs" type="FILE">
File with known short tandem repeats (STRs). This is a text file with at least three
columns: chromosome, first position and last position. Positions should be 1-based and
inclusive.
</option>
<option id="knownVariants" type="FILE">
VCF file with variants to be genotyped. Only these variants will appear in the output VCF.
With this option homozygous calls to the reference allele will be reported.
</option>
<option id="embeddedSNVs">
Flag to call SNVs within STRs. By default, STRs are treated as a single locus and hence
no SNV will be called within an STR.
</option>
<option id="minSVQuality" type="INT" default="20">
Minimum quality score (in PHRED scale) for structural variants.
</option>
<option id="genomeSize" type="INT">
Total size of the genome to use during detection of CNVs. This should be used when the reference file only includes a part of
the genome (e.g. a chromosome or a partial assembly)
</option>
<option id="binSize" type="INT" default="100">
Size of the bins to analyze read depth.
</option>
<option id="algCNV" type="STRING" default="CNVnator">
Comma-separated list of read depth algorithms to run (e.g. CNVnator,EWT).
</option>
<option id="maxPCTOverlapCNVs" type="INT" default="100 (No filter)">
Maximum percentage of overlap of a new CNV with an input CNV to include it in the output.
</option>
<option id="maxLenDeletion" type="INT" default="1000000">
Maximum length of deletions that the read-pair analysis can identify.
</option>
<option id="sizeSRSeed" type="INT" default="8">
Size of the seed to look for split-read alignments.
</option>
<option id="ignoreProperPairFlag">
With this option, the proper pair flag will not be taken into accout to decide if the ends of each fragment are properly aligned.
By default, the distribution of insert length is estimated only taking into account reads with the proper pair flag turned on.
</option>
<option id="knownSVs" type="FILE">
File with coordinates of known structural variants in GFF format.
</option>
<option id="minMQ" type="INT" default="20">
Minimum mapping quality to call an alignment unique
</option>
<option id="sampleId" type="STRING">
Id of the sample for the VCF file.
</option>
<option id="ploidy" type="INT" default="2">
Ploidy of the sample.
</option>
<option id="psp">
Print id and ploidy of the sample in the VCF header.
The header generated with this option is not a standard VCF header. However, it helps NGSEP to keep track of the ploidy of each sample through downstream analyses
</option>
<option id="runRep">
Turns on the procedure to find repetitive regions based on reads with multiple alignments.
</option>
<option id="runRD">
Turns on read depth (RD) analysis to identify CNVs.
</option>
<option id="noNewCNV">
Turns off finding new CNVs with the read depth analysis. Input CNVs and repeats will still be genotyped using the RD distribution
</option>
<option id="runRP">
Turns on read pair plus split-read analysis (RP+SR) to identify large indels and inversions.
</option>
<option id="noSNVS">
Turns off SNV detection. In this mode, only structural variation will be called
</option>
<option id="ignoreXS" deprecated="true">
Deprecated. Use minMQ option to control which alignments are considered unique
</option>
<option id="genotypeAll" deprecated="true">
Deprecated option -genotypeAll
</option>
<option id="noRep" deprecated="true">
Deprecated option -noRep. Analysis of multiple alignments to find repeats is not executed by default. Use -runRep to run this analysis
</option>
<option id="noRD" deprecated="true">
Deprecated option -noRD. Read depth analysis is not executed by default. Use -runRD to run this analysis
</option>
<option id="noRP" deprecated="true">
Deprecated option -noRP. Read pair analysis is not executed by default. Use -runRP to run this analysis
</option>
<option id="minAltCoverage" type="INT" default="0" deprecated="true">
Deprecated option -minAltCoverage
</option>
<option id="maxAltCoverage" type="INT" default="0 (No filter)"  deprecated="true">
Deprecated option -maxAltCoverage
</option>
</command>




<command id="SIH" class="ngsep.haplotyping.SingleIndividualHaplotyper" printHelp="false">
<intro>
Performs single individual molecular haplotyping
</intro>
<title>Molecular haplotyping of single individuals</title>
<description>
Performs molecular haplotyping on a single individual given a VCF and
a set of alignments in BAM format. Although theoretically it can work with
Illumina reads, it is designed to work fine with long (PacBio) reads.
Writes to standard output the phased VCF
</description>
<argument>VCF_FILE</argument>
<argument>ALIGNMENTS_FILE</argument>
<option id="a" type="STRING" default="Refhap" attribute="AlgorithmName">
Algorithm for single individual haplotypiing. It can be Refhap or DGS
</option>
</command>

<command id="MergeVariants" class="ngsep.vcf.IndividualSampleVariantsMerge">
<intro>
Generates a VCF file including the whole set of variants called in at least one of the given samples.
</intro>
<title>Merging variants from individual samples</title>
<description>
First step merging variants from different samples into an integrated VCF file.
Generates a file including the whole set of variants called in at least one sample.
The sequence names file is a text file with the ids of the sequences in the reference.
</description>
<argument>SEQUENCE_NAMES_FILE</argument>
<argument>OUTPUT_FILE</argument>
<argument multiple="true">VARIANTS_FILE</argument>
</command>

<command id="MergeVCF" class="ngsep.vcf.ConsistentVCFFilesMerge">
<intro>
Writes a final VCF file with the genotype calls for each variant on each sample.
</intro>
<title>Merging variants from individual samples</title>
<description>
Last step to merge genotype calls from different samples into an integrated VCF file.
Generates a file including the whole set of variants called for all samples.
The sequence names file is a text file with the ids of the sequences in the reference.
Writes to the standard output.
</description>
<argument>SEQUENCE_NAMES_FILE</argument>
<argument multiple="true">GENOTYPED_VARIANTS_FILE</argument>
</command>

<command id="TranscriptomeAnalyzer" class="ngsep.transcriptome.TranscriptomeAnalyzer" printHelp="false">
<intro>
Provides statistics on a transcriptome file in GFF3 format
</intro>
<title>Evaluating transcriptome assemblies</title>
<description>
Loads a transcriptome annotation in GFF3 format, logs format errors and provides statistics on the asembled transcriptome.
</description>
<argument>TRANSCRIPTOME_MAP</argument>
<argument>OUTPUT_PREFIX</argument>
<option id="g" type="GENOME" attribute="genome">
Reference genome annotated in the transcriptome file
</option>
<option id="c" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="selectCompleteProteins">
Output only complete proteins (with start and stop codons) in the proteins output file
</option>
</command>

<command id="Annotate" class="ngsep.vcf.VCFFunctionalAnnotator">
<intro>Generates a VCF file which includes the functional information related with each variant.
</intro>
<title>Functional annotation of variants</title>
<description>
Generates a VCF file including the functional information related with each variant.
Requires a VCF file, a gff3 file with gene annotations, and the reference genome in fasta format.
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>VARIANTS_FILE</argument>
<argument>TRANSCRIPTOME_MAP</argument>
<argument>REFERENCE_FILE</argument>
<option id="u" type="INT" default="1000" attribute="offsetUpstream">
Maximum bp before the start of a transcript to classify a variant as Upstream.
</option>
<option id="d" type="INT" default="300" attribute="offsetDownstream">
Maximum bp after the end of a transcript to classify a variant as Downstream.
</option>
<option id="sd" type="INT" default="2" attribute="spliceDonorOffset">
Initial basepairs of an intron that should be considered as splice donor.
</option>
<option id="sa" type="INT" default="2" attribute="spliceAcceptorOffset">
Final basepairs of an intron that should be considered as splice acceptor.
</option>
<option id="si" type="INT" default="10" attribute="spliceRegionIntronOffset">
Initial or final basepairs of an intron that should be considered as part of the splice region.
</option>
<option id="se" type="INT" default="2" attribute="spliceRegionExonOffset">
Initial or final basepairs of an exon that should be considered as part of the splice region.
</option>
</command>

<command id="FilterVCF" class="ngsep.vcf.VCFFilter">
<intro>Implements different filters on VCF files with genotype information</intro>
<title>Filtering VCF files</title>
<description>
Implement different filters on VCF files with genotype information.
first, it executes the distance filter (-d), then the filtering of
samples and genotypes (-saf, -fs, -q and -minC). Finally, it 
recalculates the number of samples genotyped, the number of alleles
called and the MAF to execute the remaining filters. Writes to the standard output.
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>INPUT_FILE</argument>
<option id="frs" type="FILE" attribute="regionsToFilter">
File with genomic regions in which variants should be filtered out.
The format of this file should contain three columns: Sequence name (chromosome), first position
in the sequence, and last position in the sequence. Both positions are assumed to be 1-based.
</option>
<option id="srs" type="FILE" attribute="regionsToSelect">
File with genomic regions in which variants should be selected.
The format of this file should contain three columns: Sequence name (chromosome), first position
in the sequence, and last position in the sequence. Both positions are assumed to be 1-based.
</option>
<option id="d" type="INT" default="0" attribute="minDistance">
Minimum distance between variants.
</option>
<option id="g" type="FILE" attribute="genome">
File with the reference genome to calculate the GC-Content of the region surrounding the variant.
</option>
<option id="minGC" type="DOUBLE" attribute="minGCContent">
Minimum percentage of GC of the 100bp region surrounding the variant.
</option>
<option id="maxGC" type="DOUBLE" attribute="maxGCContent">
Maximum percentage of GC of the 100bp region surrounding the variant.
</option>
<option id="q" type="INT" attribute="minGenotypeQuality">
Minimum genotyping quality score (GQ field in the VCF).
</option>
<option id="s" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="keepOnlySNVs">
Keep only biallelic SNVs.
</option>
<option id="fi" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="filterInvariant">
Filter out sites in which only one allele is observed.
</option>
<option id="fir" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="filterInvariantReference">
Filter sites in which only the reference allele is observed.
</option>
<option id="fia" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="filterInvariantAlternative">
Filter out sites in which only one alternative allele is observed.
</option>
<option id="minI" type="INT" default="0" attribute="minIndividualsGenotyped">
Minimum number of individuals genotyped to keep the variant.
</option>
<option id="minC" type="INT" default="0" attribute="minCoverage">
Minimum coverage to keep a genotype call.
</option>
<option id="minMAF" type="DOUBLE" default="0" attribute="minMAF">
Minimum minor allele frequency over the samples in the VCF.
</option>
<option id="maxMAF" type="DOUBLE" default="0.5" attribute="maxMAF">
Maximum minor allele frequency over the samples in the VCF.
</option>
<option id="minOH" type="DOUBLE" default="0" attribute="minOH">
Minimum observed heterozygosity over the samples in the VCF.
</option>
<option id="maxOH" type="DOUBLE" default="1" attribute="maxOH">
Maximum observed heterozygosity over the samples in the VCF.
</option>
<option id="maxCNVs" type="INT" default="-1" attribute="maxCNVs">
Maximum number of samples with copy number variation in the region where the variant is located.
</option>
<option id="gene" type="STRING" attribute="geneId">
Id of the gene or the transcript related with the variant.
</option>
<option id="a" type="STRING" attribute="annotations">
Types of functional annotations (Missense, Nonsense, Synonymous, etc) related with the variant.
More than one annotation can be set as a comma-separated list.
</option>
<option id="saf" type="FILE" attribute="sampleIds">
File with the ids of the samples to be selected (or filtered, see -fs option).
The file should have one line per sample, being the first column the sample id.
Other columns in the file are ignored.
</option>
<option id="fs" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="filterSamples">
Filter the samples provided with the -saf option instead of selecting them.
</option> 
</command>

<command id="ConvertVCF" class="ngsep.vcf.VCFConverter">
<intro>Converts genotype calls in VCF format to other formats</intro>
<title>Convert VCF files to other formats</title>
<description>
Convert genotype calls in VCF format to other formats commonly used to perform
different kinds of analysis
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>INPUT_FILE</argument>
<argument>OUTPUT_PREFIX</argument>
<option id="printStructure">
Prints input format for structure
</option>
<option id="printFasta">
Prints a virtual multiple sequence alignment
in fasta format. Useful to build distance based dendograms
</option>
<option id="printrrBLUP">
Prints input format for rrBLUP
</option>
<option id="printMatrix">
Prints genotypes in a simple ACGT format which can be imported to excel
</option>
<option id="printHapmap">
Prints Hapmap format, which can be used in programs such as Tassel
</option>
<option id="printSpagedi">
Prints the input files for Spagedi
</option>
<option id="printPlink">
Prints the input files for Plink
</option>
<option id="printHaploview">
Prints the input files for Haploview
</option>
<option id="printEmma">
Prints the input files for Emma
</option>
<option id="printPowerMarker">
Prints the input files for PowerMarker
</option>
<option id="printEigensoft">
Prints the input files for Eigensoft
</option>
<option id="printFlapjack">
Prints the input files for Flapjack
</option>
<option id="printDarwin">
Prints the input files for DarWin
</option>
<option id="printTreeMix">
Prints the input files for TreeMix.
The option -p is required for this format
</option>
<option id="printJoinMap">
Prints the input file to build genetic maps with JoinMap.
The options -p1 and -p2 are required for this format
</option>
<option id="printPhase">
Prints the input files for Phase.
The option -s is required for this format
</option>
<option id="p" type="FILE">
File with population assignments for the samples.
A two column text file with the sample ids in the
first column and the ids of the populations in the
second column. Required for conversion to TreeMix
</option>
<option id="p1" type="STRING">
Id of the first parent for conversion to JoinMap
</option>
<option id="p2" type="STRING">
Id of the second parent for conversion to JoinMap
</option>
<option id="s" type="STRING">
Name of the sequence (chromosome) for conversion to PHASE.
</option>
</command>

<command id="QualStats" class="ngsep.alignments.BasePairQualityStatisticsCalculator">
<intro> Detects sequencing error biases</intro>
<title>Calculating base quality statistics</title>
<description>
This module takes one or more sets of alignments and a reference genome and
counts the number of mismatches with the reference for each read position from
5' to 3' end. This report is useful to detect sequencing error biases.
Requires alignment files to be in SAM|BAM format, and the reference genome that
was used to produce the alignments.
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>REFERENCE_FILE</argument>
<argument multiple="true">ALIGNMENTS_FILE</argument>
<option id="ignoreXS" deprecated="true">
Deprecated. Use minMQ option to control which alignments are considered unique
</option>
<option id="minMQ" type="INT" default="20" attribute="minMQ">
Minimum mapping quality to call an alignment unique
</option>
</command>

<command id="CoverageStats" class="ngsep.discovery.CoverageStatisticsCalculator">
<intro>Shows the uniformity of the sequencing process over the genome</intro>
<title>Calculating coverage statistics</title>
<description>
This module calculates the number of base pairs that are covered by reads at
each coverage level from 1 to a maximum. Alignments must be in SAM|BAM format.
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>ALIGNMENTS_FILE</argument>
<argument>OUTPUT_FILE</argument>
<option id="minMQ" type="INT" default="20" attribute="minMQ">
Minimum mapping quality to call an alignment unique
</option>
</command>

<command id="CompareVCF" class="ngsep.vcf.VCFComparator">
<intro>Compares the genotype calls included in two different VCF files</intro>
<title>Comparing VCF files</title>
<description>
Compare the genotype calls included in two different VCF files.
Calculate the number and percentage of homozygous and heterozygous
differences between every pair of samples.
The first required argument is the FASTA file with the reference genome used to generate the VCF files
Writes to the standard output.
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>REFERENCE_FILE</argument>
<argument>FIRST_VCF_FILE</argument>
<argument>SECOND_VCF_FILE</argument>
<option id="g" type="DOUBLE" default="50" attribute="minPCTGenotyped">
Minimum percentage (0-100) of variants genotyped in both samples
</option>
<option id="d" type="DOUBLE" default="5" attribute="maxPCTDiffs">
Maximum percentage (0-100) of differences between the pair of samples
</option>
</command>

<command id="SummaryStats" class="ngsep.vcf.VCFSummaryStatisticsCalculator">
<intro>Generates a report with the numbers of variants included in a VCF file for different categories.</intro>
<title>Calculating summary statistics</title>
<description>
Generate a report with the variants included in a VCF file for different categories.
It is specially useful when a complete population is being processed and merged into a
single annotated file. Writes to the standard output
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>INPUT_FILE</argument>
<option id="m" type="INT" default="20" attribute="minSamplesGenotyped">
Minimum number of samples genotyped to accurately calculate the minor allele frequency
</option>
</command>

<command id="DiversityStats" class="ngsep.vcf.VCFDiversityCalculator">
<intro>
Calculates basic diversity statistics for each variant in a VCF file.
</intro>
<title>Calculating diversity statistics per site</title>
<description>
Calculate basic diversity statistics for each variant in a VCF file.
The populations file is a tab-delimited text file with two columns: sample id and population id.
Writes to the standard output. See the README.txt file for details on the output. 
</description>
<argument>INPUT_FILE</argument>
<argument>POPULATIONS_FILE</argument>
</command>

<command id="VCFVariantDensityCalculator" class="ngsep.vcf.VCFVariantDensityCalculator">
<intro>
Calculates the density of variants in a VCF file across the genome 
</intro>
<title>Calculating variants density</title>
<description>
Calculates the number of variants within a VCF file in non-overlapping windows across the genome.
Writes to the standard output a text delimited file with four columns: sequence, window first,
window last and number of variants
</description>
<argument>VCF_FILE</argument>
<option id="w" type="INT" defaultConstant="DEF_WINDOW_LENGTH" attribute="windowLength">
Length of the window
</option>
</command>

<command id="VCFDistanceMatrixCalculator" class="ngsep.vcf.VCFDistanceMatrixCalculator">
<intro>
Calculates a genetic distance matrix from genomic variants in a given VCF file
</intro>
<title>Calculation of genetic distance matrices from VCF files</title>
<description>
Generates a distance matrix from a variants file in VCF format.
The matrix is calculated using the basic IBS (Identity by state) algorithm. However, four
options to infer the genotype call information are implemented. In particular, users can
choose predicted allele dosages of CNVs or direct estimations of allele dosage per site
per individual based on relative allele-specific read counts. The latter option is useful
to improve distance estimations in polyploids.
It writes to standard output the matrix of genetic distances in a generic format.
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>VCF_FILE</argument>

<option id="t" type="INT" default="0" attribute="matrixType">
Matrix output format, 0 is full matrix, 1 lower-left matrix and 2 is upper right matrix.
</option>
<option id="s" type="INT" default="0" attribute="distanceSource">
Source of information in the VCF file to calculate distances. 0 for simple genotype calls (GT format field),
1 for allele copy number (ACN format field), 2 for total copy number (total of ACN format field),
and 3 for raw allele depth (ADP or BSDP format fields) 
</option>
<option id="p" type="INT" default="2" attribute="ploidy">
Default ploidy of the samples. Used if the distance source (-s option) is the raw allele depths
to recalculate allele dosage based on these counts 
</option>
</command>

<command id="NeighborJoining" class="ngsep.clustering.NeighborJoining">
<intro>
Construct a neighbor joining dendogram given a distance matrix file
</intro>
<title>Building dendograms using the Neighbor-Joining algorithm</title>
<description>
Given a distance matrix file, this command builds a dendogram for graphical display of genetic
distances using the Neighbor Joining algorithm. The distance matrix can be provided as an upper, lower
or full matrix. The dendogram is written to standard output in Newick format.
</description>
<argument>MATRIX_FILE</argument>
</command>

<command id="AlleleSharingStats" class="ngsep.vcf.AlleleSharingStatsCalculator">
<intro>
Calculates allele sharing diversity statistics, either through windows or through genes
for inbred populations
</intro>
<title>Calculating allele sharing statistics</title>
<description>
Calculates allele sharing diversity statistics, either through windows across the genome 
or through the genes catalog of the species. This program calculates the pairwise differences between
every pair of samples in the VCF file and uses that information to calculate diversity statistics such
as the average number of pairwise differences per Kbp, Fst and Tajima D. This functionality should only
be applied to VCFs containing populations of inbred samples. Each group can either be one or more than
populations wthin the populations file. Multiple population names within one group should be separated
by comma (without white spaces).
The populations file is a tab-delimited text file with two columns: sample id and population id.
Writes to the standard output. See the README.txt file for details on the output.
</description>
<argument>VCF_FILE</argument>
<argument>POPULATIONS_FILE</argument>
<argument>GROUP_1</argument>
<argument>GROUP_2</argument>
<option id="t" type="FILE">
GFF3 file with the transcriptome. If this file is provided, statistics will be provided by gene and
not by window.
</option>
<option id="i">
If set, introns will be included in the calculation of pairwise differences. Only useful if the
-t option is set
</option>
<option id="w" type="INT" default="100000">
Length of each genomic window to calculate pairwise differences between samples. 
</option>
<option id="s" type="INT" default="10000">
Step between windows to calculate pairwise differences between samples.
</option>
</command>

<command id="ImputeVCF" class="ngsep.variants.imputation.GenotypeImputer">
<intro>
Imputes missing genotypes from unphased multilocus SNP genotype data in a VCF.
</intro>
<title>Genotype imputation</title>
<description>
Impute missing genotypes from unphased multilocus SNP genotype data in a VCF.
* Only biallelic SNPs are imputed and included in the output VCF file.
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>VCF_FILE</argument>
<argument>OUT_PREFIX</argument>
<option id="p" type="STRING" attribute="parentIds">
Comma-separated list of sample ids of the parents of the population.
Only to be used for bi-parental or multi-parental breeding populations.
</option>
<option id="k" type="INT" default="8" attribute="k">
Maximum number of groups in which local haplotypes will be clustered.
For bi-parental or multi-parental breeding populations please set explicitly
the number of parents of the population even if the list of parents is provided with the
-p option. This allows to take into account cases of populations in which some of
the parents are missing
</option>
<option id="w" type="INT" default="5000" attribute="windowSize">
Size of the window to process variants at the same time
</option>
<option id="o" type="INT" default="50" attribute="overlap">
Overlap between windows
</option>
<option id="c" type="DOUBLE" default="0.001" attribute="avgCMPerKbp">
Estimated average number of centiMorgans per Kbp on euchromatic regions of the genome.
Typical values of this parameter are 0.001 for human populations, 0.004 for rice and 0.35
for yeast populations
</option>
<option id="t" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="skipTransitionsTraining">
If set, transition probabilities in the HMM will NOT be updated during the Baum-Welch
training of the HMM. Not recommended unless the -c option is set to a value allowing a
reasonable initial estimation of the transition probabilities.
</option>
<option id="ip" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="inbredParents">
Specifies that parents of the population are inbreds
</option>
<option id="is" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="inbredSamples">
Specifies that the samples to impute are inbreds
</option>
</command>

<command id="IntrogressionAnalysis" class="ngsep.vcf.VCFWindowIntrogressionAnalysis">
<intro>Runs a window-based haplotype introgression analysis.</intro>
<title>Finding haplotype introgressions</title>
<description>
Runs a window-based analysis to identify the most common haplotype within each of the
populations described in the given populations file and then identify common haplotypes
of one population introgressed in samples of a different population. Although it can be
run on any VCF file, it is particularly designed to work with populations of inbred
samples. 
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>VCF_FILE</argument>
<argument>POPULATIONS_FILE</argument>
<argument>OUT_PREFIX</argument>
<option id="p" type="DOUBLE" default="80" attribute="minPctGenotyped">
Minimum percentage of samples genotyped within a population to identify the most common
allele.
</option>
<option id="d" type="DOUBLE" default="0.6" attribute="minDiffAF">
Minimum difference between reference allele frequencies of at least two populations
to consider a variant discriminative.
</option>
<option id="m" type="DOUBLE" default="0.4" attribute="maxMAFWithin">
Maximum minor allele frequency within a population to consider the major allele of a
variant as representative allele for such population.
</option>
<option id="w" type="INT" default="50" attribute="windowSize">
Window size as number of variants within each window
</option>
<option id="o" type="INT" default="0" attribute="overlap">
Overlap as number of variants shared between neighbor windows
</option>
<option id="a" type="INT" default="1" attribute="matchScore">
Score given of a match between homozygous genotypes comparing haplotypes
</option>
<option id="i" type="INT" default="-1" attribute="mismatchScore">
Score given of a mismatch between homozygous genotypes comparing haplotypes
</option>
<option id="s" type="INT" default="30" attribute="minScore">
Minimum score to match an individual haplotype with a population-derived haplotype
</option>
<option id="v" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="printVCF">
Outputs a VCF file with the biallelic variants that showed segregation between at least one
pair of groups and hence were selected for the analysis. 
</option>
<option id="u" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="printUnassigned">
If set, reports introgression events for unassigned haplotypes according to the minimum score defined by
the options -a -i and -s
</option>
</command>

<command id="Demultiplex" class="ngsep.sequencing.ReadsDemultiplex">
<intro>
Builds individual fastq files for different samples from
a single file containing reads from a whole sequencing lane (Former Deconvolute)
</intro>
<title>Demultiplexing reads</title>
<description>
Build individual fastq files for different samples from a single file containing the reads
for a whole sequencing lane in which several samples were barcoded and sequenced.
INDEX_FILE is a tab-delimited file with four columns by default: flowcell, lane, barcode
and sampleID. If the -a option for dual barcode is activated, five columns are expected:
flowcell, lane, barcode1, barcode2 and sampleID. The file must have a header line. The same
index file can be used to demultiplex several FASTQ files. Out FASTQ files will be gzip
compressed by default
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>INDEX_FILE</argument>
<argument>FASTQ_FILE_1</argument>
<argument>FASTQ_FILE_2</argument>
<option id="o" type="DIR" attribute="outDirectory">
Directory where the output fastq files will be saved.
</option>
<option id="t" type="STRING" attribute="trimSequence">
If this sequence is found within a read, the read will be trimmed up to the start of this sequence.
</option>
<option id="u" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="uncompressedOutput">
Output uncompressed files.
</option>
<option id="r" type="INT" attribute="minReadLength">
Minimum read length to keep a read after trimming adapter sequences
</option>
<option id="a" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="dualBarcode">
Activate demultiplexing with dual barcoding.
</option>
<option id="d" type="FILE" attribute="laneFilesDescriptor" >
Tab-delimited file listing the lane FASTQ files to be demultiplexed. Columns are: Flowcell, lane and
fastq file (which can be gzip compressed). A second fastq file can be specified for pair-end sequencing.
If the reads sequenced for one lane are split in multiple files, each file (or each pair of files)
should be included in a separate row. If this option is used, the options -f, -l and the input fastq
file(s) are ignored
</option>
<option id="f" type="STRING" attribute="flowcell">
Id of the flowcell corresponding to the input fastq file(s). Required if -d option is not specified.
</option>
<option id="l" type="STRING" attribute="lane">
Id of the lane corresponding to the input fastq file(s). Required if the -d option is not specified.
</option>
</command>

<command id="CompareRD" class="ngsep.discovery.rd.CNVseqAlgorithm">
<intro>
Compares the read depth of two samples
</intro>
<title>Comparing read depth between samples</title>
<description>
Compares the read depth between two samples to identify copy number variation.
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>ALIGNMENTS_FILE_1</argument>
<argument>ALIGNMENTS_FILE_2</argument>
<argument>REFERENCE</argument>
<argument>OUT_PREFIX</argument>
<option id="binSize" type="INT" default="100">
Window size to be used during the read depth comparison.
</option>
<option id="p" type="FLOAT" default="0.001">
Maximum p-value. Only the windows with a p-value
lower than that specified will be reported.
</option>
<option id="w">
Output an entry for every window in the genome.
</option>
<option id="g">
Perform GC-correction of the read depth.
</option>
<option id="b">
Perform the Bonferroni correction for multiple testing.
</option>
</command>

<command id="KmersCounter" class="ngsep.sequences.KmersCounter">
<intro>
Obtains the distribution of k-mer abundances
</intro>
<title>Obtaining k-mers spectrum from sequences</title>
<description>
Generate a distribution of k-mer abundances from a file of DNA sequences either in fastq or in fasta format.
Writes to standard output the number of k-mers obtained at each specific read depth
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>SEQUENCES_FILE</argument>
<option id="b" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="bothStrands">
Count k-mers from both strands.
</option>
<option id="k" type="INT" defaultConstant="DEFAULT_KMER_SIZE" attribute="kmerSize">
K-mer length
</option>
<option id="fasta" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="fasta">
Input is a fasta file.
</option>
</command>

<command id="DeNovoGBS" class="ngsep.gbs.KmerPrefixReadsClusteringAlgorithm" printHelp="false">
<intro>
De novo variants discovery from a GBS experiment
</intro>
<title>GBS deNovo variants discovery</title>
<description>
Performs de novo variants discovery from a GBS experiment
</description>
<argument>INPUT_DIRECTORY</argument>
<argument>OUTPUT_DIRECTORY</argument>
<option id="k" type="INT" defaultConstant="DEF_KMER_LENGTH" attribute="kmerLength">
K-mer length
</option>
</command>

<command id="RelativeAlleleCounts" class="ngsep.discovery.BAMRelativeAlleleCountsCalculator">
<intro>
Calculates the distribution of relative allele counts 
</intro>
<title>Obtaining relative allele counts from read alignment files</title>
<description>
Calculates a distribution of relative allele counts for sites showing base calls for more than one
nucleotide from read alignment files in BAM format. This analysis is useful to predict the ploidy
of a sequenced sample.
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>ALIGNMENTS_FILE</argument>
<option id="m" type="INT" default="10" attribute="minRD">
Minimum read depth
</option>
<option id="M" type="INT" default="1000" attribute="maxRD">
Maximum read depth
</option>
<option id="q" type="INT" default="20" attribute="minBaseQualityScore">
Minimum base quality score (Phred scale)
</option>
<option id="r" type="FILE" attribute="repeatsFile">
File with repeats (or any kind of genomic regions) that should not be taken into account in the analysis.
The format of this file should contain three columns: Sequence name (chromosome), first position
in the sequence, and last position in the sequence. Both positions are assumed to be 1-based.
</option>
<option id="f" type="FILE" attribute="selectedRegionsFile">
File with genomic regions that should be taken into account in the analysis.
The format of this file should contain three columns: Sequence name (chromosome), first position
in the sequence, and last position in the sequence. Both positions are assumed to be 1-based.
</option>
<option id="s" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="secondaryAlns">
Consider secondary alignments. By default, only primary alignments are processed
</option>
</command>

<command id="SingleIndividualSimulator" class="ngsep.simulation.SingleIndividualSimulator">
<intro>
Simulates a single individual with homozygous and heterozygous mutations from a reference genome
</intro>
<title>Simulating individuals from a reference genome</title>
<description>
This simulator takes a (haploid) genome assembly and simulates a single individual including
homozygous and heterozygous mutations (SNPs, indels and mutated STRs) relative to the input assembly.
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>GENOME</argument>
<argument>OUT_PREFIX</argument>

<option id="s" type="DOUBLE" defaultConstant="DEF_SNV_RATE" attribute="snvRate">
Proportion of reference basepairs with simulated SNV events
</option>
<option id="i" type="DOUBLE" defaultConstant="DEF_INDEL_RATE" attribute="indelRate">
Proportion of reference basepairs with simulated indel events
</option>
<option id="f" type="DOUBLE" defaultConstant="DEF_MUTATED_STR_FRACTION" attribute="mutatedSTRFraction">
Fraction of input STRs for which a mutation will be simulated
</option>
<option id="t" type="FILE" attribute="strsFile">
Path to a text file describing the known STRs in the given genome
</option>
<option id="u" type="INT" defaultConstant="DEF_STR_UNIT_INDEX" attribute="strUnitIndex">
Zero-based index in the STR file where the unit sequence is located
</option>
<option id="d" type="STRING" defaultConstant="DEF_SAMPLE_ID" attribute="sampleId">
ID of the simulated sample. Appears in the VCF header and as part of the name of the sequences in the
simulated genome
</option>
<option id="p" type="INT" defaultConstant="DEF_PLOIDY" attribute="ploidy">
Ploidy of the simulated sample 
</option>
</command>
<command id="GenomesAligner" class="ngsep.genome.GenomesAligner">
<intro>
Compares two partially or completely assembled genomes
</intro>
<title>Comparing genomes</title>
<description>
Takes two assembled genomes in fasta format and their corresponding transcriptomes in GFF3 format
and runs a whole genome comparison taking unique genes as orthology units
</description>
<argument>OPTIONS</argument>
<argument>GENOME1</argument>
<argument>TRANSCRIPTOME1</argument>
<argument>GENOME2</argument>
<argument>TRANSCRIPTOME2</argument>
<option id="o" type="STRING" defaultConstant="DEF_OUT_PREFIX" attribute="outPrefix">
Prefix of output files
</option>
<option id="k" type="INT" defaultConstant="DEF_KMER_SIZE" attribute="kmerSize">
K-mer size to find orthologs
</option>
<option id="p" type="INT" defaultConstant="DEF_MIN_PCT_KMERS" attribute="minPctKmers">
Minimum percentage of k-mers to find orthologs
</option>
</command>

<command id="VCFIndividualGenomeBuilder" class="ngsep.vcf.VCFIndividualGenomeBuilder">
<intro>
Builds a genome in fasta format from homozygous variants in a VCF file
</intro>
<title>Building genomes from variants</title>
<description>
Takes a VCF file with genotype information from one sample and the reference genome used to build
the VCF and generates a new genome in fasta format modified using the alternative alleles from
variants called as homozygous alternative within the individual. This can be useful to perform 
polishing of new genome assemblies using Illumina data, or in general to construct a haploid version
of an individual genome 
</description>
<argument>VCF_FILE</argument>
<argument>REFERENCE_GENOME</argument>
<argument>OUT_GENOME</argument>
</command>

<command id="VCFGoldStandardComparator" class="ngsep.benchmark.VCFGoldStandardComparator">
<intro>
Compares a gold standard phased VCF with a VCF with test genotype calls
</intro>
<title>Benchmarking variant calls</title>
<description>
Takes a VCF file with genotype information from one sample, the reference genome used to build
the VCF and a phased VCF file with gold standard calls and calculates quality statistics
comparing gold-standard with test calls. See the README.txt file for details on the output.
</description>
<argument>REFERENCE_GENOME</argument>
<argument>GS_VCF_FILE</argument>
<argument>TEST_VCF_FILE</argument>
<option id="m" type="FILE" attribute="complexRegions">
File with coordinates of complex regions (such as STRs)
</option>
<option id="f" type="FILE" attribute="confidenceRegions">
File with coordinates of regions in which the gold standard can be trusted 
</option>
<option id="g" type="BOOLEAN" attribute="genomicVCF">
Indicates that the gold standard VCF is genomic, which means that confidence regions can be
extracted from annotated regions with homozygous reference genotypes   
</option>
</command>

</NGSEP>
